A Guide to the Papers of Charles Fort, 1920-1951
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Charles Fort, 1920-1951
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7657-a
This collection consists of 835 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased on 1965 Jan 1.
Scope and Content Information
Fort's correspondence discusses the submission of God and the Fishmonger to his publishers, and Victor Gollancz's rejection of Wild Talents; the founding of the Fortean society; Lo! and the reviews it has received; and research into occult powers. Tiffany Thayer comments on dianetics and L. Ron Hubbard; Fort comments on Irving Babbitt and Baron Karl Von Reichenbach.
Collection also includes clippings from American and foreign newspapers and magazines re Book of the Damned, New Lands, Lo!, and Wild Talents; printed letters and circulars re Lo! and Wild Talents; pamphlets and application forms for the Fortean Society; and a typescript with corrections of Lo!.
Correspondents include Curtis Brown, Ltd.; Nelson Bond; Ruth D'Agostino; Martin Kamin; Claude Kendall; Aaron Sussman; Monroe Upton; Nathan Wallack; and Tiffany Thayer.
Contents List
- Manuscript: Lo![1930], TMs. w/autograph correct. 467 p.
- Letters
  - Elmer Ellsworth, Jr. [Tiffany Thayer] to (carbon) Charles Fort 1930 Apr 29, TL. 1 p.
    Has read part of God and the Fishmonger and has submitted it to his publisher. Comments on the work.
  - T. T. to Mr. Cope [encl. 3 clippings and 10 copies of form letter re Fortean Society] 1931 Jan 22, TL. 1 p.
    Offers enclosed information re Fortean Society. Mentions some new members, Alexander Woollcott, Harry Leon Wilson, Charles G. Norris. Form letter, dated 21 Jan 1931 announces first meeting of Fortean Society with founder members.
  - Monroe Upton to Claude Kendall [encl. 3 p. TMs (carbon) of Upton review of Lo!] 1931 Feb 25, TLS. 1 p.
    Thanks for copy of Lo! Sends enclosed review, and reports on friends' acquaintance with the book. Offers to advertise other books.
  - Martin Kamin to Aaron Sussman [encl. 1 p. invitation to the Fortean Society] 1931 Mar 12, TLS. 1 p.
    Requests display material and ten copies of first edition of Lo!.
  - [Curtis Brown, Ltd.] to A. S. (carbon) 1932 Apr 28, TLS. 1 p.
    Reports that Messrs. Victor Gollancz have declined Wild Talents.
  - Ruth D'Agostico to A. S. n. d., TLS. 1 p.
    Requests an appointment with Miss Brown. Enthuses over Lo!.
- Miscellaneous
  - Re: Book of the Damned1920, Clippings. 10 items.
  - Re: New Lands 1923-26, Clippings. ca. 30 items.
  - Re: Charles Fort and Lo!1930, Clippings. 3 items.
  - Re: Lo! from New York papers 1931, Clippings. 300 items.
  - Re: Lo! from New Jersey and Penn. papers 1931, Clippings. 41 items.
  - Re: Lo! from New England papers 1931, Clippings. 20 items.
  - Re: Lo! from Southern papers 1931, Clippings. 37 items.
  - Re: Lo! from Midwestern papers 1931, Clippings. 61 items.
  - Re: Lo! from Western papers 1931, Clippings. 22 items.
  - Re: Lo! from foreign papers 1931, Clippings. 42 items.
  - Re: Fort's unexplainable phenomena 1931, Clippings. 9 items.
  - Reviews of Lo!, Book of the Damned, and New Lands1931, Magazines. 5 items.
  - Re: Wild Talents, death of Fort; from New York papers 1932, Clippings. 81 items.
  - Re: Wild Talents, death of Fort; from New Jersey and Penn. papers 1932, Clippings. 13 items.
  - Re: Wild Talents, death of Fort; from New England papers 1932, Clippings.
    21 items
  - Re: Wild Talents, death of Fort; from Southern papers 1932, Clippings. 35 items.
  - Re: Wild Talents, death of Fort; from Midwestern papers 1932, Clippings. 37 items.
  - Re: Wild Talents, death of Fort; from Western papers 1932, Clippings. 15 items.
  - Re: Wild Talents, death of Fort; from Canadian papers 1932, Clippings. 3 items.
  - Articles re: Wild Talents1932, Magazines. 5 items
  - Re: Wild Talents and Lo!1932, Clippings. 2 items.
  - Claude Kendall to Book Buyers re Lo!1931 Jan 28, Printed. 9 letter items.
  - Re: Lo! and Wild Talents circulars and letters [1931-32], Printed. 8 items.
  - For Fortean Society and application forms n. d., Pamphlets. 10 items.